Welcome
to a live episode of
Houston, We Have a Podcast.
We are getting in front of the cameras,
today because if you haven't heard,
NASA is accepting, applications
to become an astronaut,
all throughout the month of March.
So, we have got a lot of questions,
and we have great guests,
here that are going to be answering,
them for you live.
Make sure you follow,
along
with us on Facebook
and Twitter, and wherever else.
We got—
we will be getting to your
questions, here in a second,
but I like to first introduce our,
very special guest.
Starting with Ann Romer.
Ann, welcome.
Thank you, glad to be here.
You are the manager of the
astronaut, selection office.
You know the ins,
and outs of the application process,
and you're there from the inside.
In fact, you came on the podcast—
you actually help.
Let's kick
it off with episode two to talk,
about when we brought on the astronaut,
twenty seventeen class.
I remember that very well.
Well, welcome back.
Thank you.
I'm curious to hear the insides of this.
Thanks.
We also have Kayla Baron.
Hey Kayla, hi.
Carey, Caleb,
Caleb—you're
among the turtles—the astronaut class of
twenty seventeen—
you went through this application process,
and competed against eighteen thousand
other people.
And you're here,
and you're part of the turtles.
You have a bachelor's in
systems, engineering with a,
from the U.S.
Naval Academy and a master's in nuclear,
engineering from Cambridge.
You are a marine warfare officer,
and you just graduated two months ago.
Congratulations!
Thank you.
How's how's life been after graduation?
It's
been awesome.
We've been really busy doing lots of
different jobs now that we've graduated,
still in training as well,
but it's been a lot of fun to contribute to the
office in a different way.
Wonderful.
Okay, well, I have a
lot of questions,
but we also are going to be taking,
questions live from you, from the viewer,
and we have Jennifer Hernandez
standing by.
Hey Jennifer, hey there.
Gary, Hey Kayla, hey Ann.
Jennifer works with
us in our public,
affairs office.
She's also a fellow Penn Stater.
We are Penn State.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
We're going to be taking questions live.
The Ohioan's rolling her eyes.
Well, the fellow Penn, Stater is going to be
taking questions.
I don't know about that.
Yeah, we'll see.
From the web,
Jeff, do we have any questions to start
us off?
We sure do.
We have one from Twitter from Celery:
what do you have to do to stand,
out from all the other applicants?
That's a good question.
I think that question is for me.
Yeah, yeah, no, I'm just teasing.
Right, So we We are looking for a lot of
information on the resume that folks fill out.
So I would start by saying,
right, we want people to be very detailed
as they, describe their work experience,
and other experiences.
We also give,
applicants an opportunity to describe,
hobbies and interests that they have,
and we encourage applicants to put as much,
information there as possible as well.
When you're reviewing eighteen thousand
applications,
sometimes it's
the weird stuff that stands, out honestly,
an interesting hobby or an interesting,
project at work that right
an applicant may think, oh,
that's just what I do,
and so really we're looking for them to give,
us as much information
as possible.
Okay, that's a starting point.
That's a starting point for standing out.
Let's get into the details of what,
you need just in the first place.
Right?
So what's the—let's
start from the very minimum,
requirements.
What are you looking for as as a minimum,
requirement to become a NASA astronaut?
The minimum requirements are pretty,
straightforward, Gary.
We are— we require a master's
degree,
and that's actually,
something that's new this year.
We have always stated in our,
application process that advanced,
degrees are preferred.
This is just trying to be a little bit
more overt in what we're looking for,
in that most the majority of astronauts
have had a master's degree or beyond,
or test pilot school.
They also, beyond the degree,
have to have at least two,
years of professional experience,
and
then, being a
U.S. government agency,
we also require U.S. citizenship.
Very important.
Okay, so yeah, master's degree.
I guess you had to deal with the eighteen
thousand applications
last time, right?
But it turns out,
I guess, this twenty seventeen class had a
lot of master's anyway.
Is that is it sort of just narrowing in on
what, you already know that you're looking
for?
And in the announcement, I encourage,
applicants to review the announcement,
online.
It's got a lot of specifics
that can count,
towards a master's degree,
etc.
So read the announcement.
It's got all the information that folks,
need to know whether
they're qualified, or not.
Now this might be a stupid question,
but
STEM—you know—we always talk about STEM
science,
technology, engineering,
math.
Why?
said Science, technology, engineering,
method?
I'm a marketing major.
I want to go to space.
Why can't I go?
I've heard that from a lot of people lately.
Right,
the the.
A
core component of what
we're, asking folks
to do and to train,
and Kayla can probably,
speak to
this
as well, right,
there's a technical technological
component of that,
and so a lot of the jobs at NASA,
require that STEM background.
So.
Okay, yeah, it's ultimately.
Well, how has it helped you,
Kayla, with just some of your astronaut
candidate,
training having that STEM background?
How has it helped you in
just the first,
few years of training?
That's a really good question.
I think in our training,
we're really generalists.
We're asked to understand,
and be able to operate in a lot of different,
contexts—whether
that's learning how to operate,
systems on the space station,
or fly a T-38,
or even work in Mission Control.
And so I think having
a tech—you know—a STEM background of
some kind helps,
give you
sort of the baseline skills,
you need to understand those things.
Because a lot gets thrown
at you, really fast,
so having a foundation that even though,
people come from a lot of different,
areas—whether that's
geology, microbiology,
engineering,
aviation, different parts of the military,
medicine—it kind of gives you a starting,
point to approach a lot of those problems.
Yeah,
that's huge because you don't—
you have to train on so many
different areas, right?
So having a baseline to be able to tackle,
all of these different
problems—STEM is probably,
one of the best ways to do that.
Very interesting.
So you talked about related experience.
Is it, so I'm assuming,
it has to deal with the related,
experience of what you have a degree in?
Yeah, right,
and there's some flexibility.
For example,
though, right, finishing a.
your degree,
and your master's degree,
and going in working as
a ski instructor—although fun and
wonderful—wouldn't,
we wouldn't, count that towards the two-year,
professional experience.
So it would need to be in a discipline.
Ideally equated with the
degree, we see right—some of the more,
general physics is an example.
You can get a degree in physics,
and do a lot of different things.
So we're looking for that.
Technology experience
that, that technological experience,
beyond the degree.
Beyond the degree.
Okay.
Now, what if you're a pilot?
Is there a little bit different,
scenario there?
Pilots, um.
You know, and it's interesting.
We still use,
in Kalo,
I'm sure we'll talk about this as well.
We still use the T-38 as a training,
vehicle, and so we do
still have pilot,
astronauts in the astronaut office.
If applying
to, as a pilot.
Uh, folks need to have a minimum of a
thousand,
hours of pilot in command type.
Pilot in command,
hours in a high performance jet aircraft.
Okay, and Kayla, I'm
guessing
now—you were not a
pilot—you have various engineering
degrees—but
you're training in the T-38 anyway.
Yeah, so we our class has a
number of pilots,
but also a number of people from different,
backgrounds.
My background is in the submarine,
force in the Navy,
so after,
graduating from my master's program,
I went through the Navy's nuclear power,
training and then worked in a very,
operational context aboard submarines,
deploying in the Pacific.
So that was kind of applying engineering,
and that's how I got my.
You know years of professional,
experience that Ann is talking about,
but when we come here,
even if you're not a pilot, you learn how to fly.
So we train to fly
in the back, seat of the T-38.
thirty eight.
Originally in a role kind of doing,
communications and navigation,
but once we get qualified,
we
also help fly the jet too.
So, we use, it as an opportunity to train
with other,
crewmates, other astronauts,
to learn how to communicate, when you're in
a high-risk environment,
operating real machinery,
make decisions when things aren't going,
according to plan and things like that.
See, I feel like this communication,
aspect
has got to be a big, part of being an astronaut.
Cause what we're talking about,
now is when we're talking about this,
new class of astronauts.
And we can actually, bring up
the application here in a second.
But we're talking about this Artemis,
generation—you're talking about,
people who are going to be going
to different,
planets and have to live, together for a long
period of time.
They have to coexist.
So getting along with your,
crewmates has got to be pretty important.
Do you find that in
the turtles,
or do you guys get along with each other?
Yeah, we get along really great.
I think graduation was really,
fun for us as a group,
because it was just a huge,
accomplishment for us as a team.
I mean, you get here and you start training,
and a lot is being asked of you,
and most of
our evaluations are really,
about our individual skills,
and performance.
You're kind of in the hot seat alone,
but we,
chose to approach our training as a team,
and wanted everybody to get to the finish,
line together.
And that made a huge difference for us
because everybody had something that they
were really naturally good at,
and everyone
also on the other side had something that
was harder for them than they might have
expected.
And so having the support of your peers,
made all of the difference in the world.
And we also do specific training geared,
towards getting to know each other,
and become good teammates.
We do things
like we went on a backpacking,
course with NOLS in the
Canyon, Lands in Utah.
That was really fun.
We also incorporate that kind of training,
whenever we're doing other,
kinds of training as well.
So we, get that kind of training in the Neutral,
Buoyancy Lab when you're,
working with a teammate,
practicing spacewalks skills or,
things like our geology training,
where we go out in the field,
and try to
learn about the geology of our,
planet so that we can apply that in future,
exploration.
But a lot of that is about,
working as a
team, doing that in a group,
and taking advantage of everybody's,
skill sets to accomplish a mission.
I really want to go into what it's, like just these
first couple years,
but first I,
want to take a look at the application,
and see what people can actually do.
So in order to go
to apply to be an astronaut,
thank you Jennifer, to for taking us here.
We're going to take a look at USA Jobs.
If you're, looking to apply to become an
astronaut,
I would assume,
you would just search the title astronaut.
There it is, astronaut candidate.
Okay, because you're a candidate for the first,
couple of years.
Okay, so you would go there,
you would click on Linda B.
Johnson Space Center.
That's where
we are today.
And here you go.
This is the application process,
and actually,
I've gone through this a couple times.
It's it's pretty dense.
There's a lot to it,
a lot of different responsibilities.
My favorite though is that one right there:
'Extensive travel required.'
Kayla,
I'm sure you're going to have to go,
many different places all over the world,
outside of the world.
There's, going to be an expectation of
being a NASA, astronaut.
Let's see.
Specialized.
Okay, here's a good section right here.
The degree fields—
what, when related to sciences—
because... Okay, here's—
that's a good point.
Because we're talking about STEM,
right?
We've said that science, technology,
engineering, math.
Degrees in technology are actually not
considered qualifying.
That's interesting.
Are there, but it looks like
even some sciences though.
So what, looking at what's not what
you, what's not considered qualifying?
What, give me some examples of different,
engineering,
math, sciences that you're looking for.
So right, I think
engineering—
we probably see the majority of degrees,
coming from aerospace engineering,
mechanical engineering, electrical
engineering,
calculus— sitting here next to me with
systems,
engineering and also nuclear engineering.
So I think I think the majority of engineering,
disciplines,
we've probably had applications or,
candidates come from,
in the science arena.
Right, we have biological science majors.
We have the physical science majors.
We have, we see a lot of applications from
medical, doctors,
and that's an important skill,
set for the astronaut office to have and,
continue to have available to us as we,
look at putting together long duration, cruise,
etc.
So, yeah, most
of the degrees that aren't,
qualifying are listed there,
you know,
as as curriculums change and majors evolve.
If there's ever any doubt,
we actually do research the degree,
program,
and look at the amount of math, and science
classes that are required.
So if If there is a questionable degree,
we actually do the research,
and make sure that it would be qualifying.
Okay.
Now, Kayla, what made you want
to pursue systems,
engineering and then nuclear engineering?
When you were in school,
what were you thinking about?
Um.
Anne probably knows,
this from pursuing applications,
but systems,
engineering means a lot of different,
things at a lot of different, universities at the
Naval Academy.
It's actually Control Systems,
and Robotics Engineering.
So I was attracted to that major initially,
because it was super interdisciplinary.
I liked electrical engineering, I liked coding,
and I liked, doing things
with an application focus.
And
so that was a good fit for me because,
I
got to dabble in a lot of different,
types of engineering,
and also work on bringing those,
disciplines together to accomplish,
something really tangible,
and
I found that really attractive.
And then during my time at the Naval,
Academy, I got really interested in
climate change,
and new energy,
technologies that would help,
us to deal with that longer term,
and I came to feel
that nuclear was a huge,
part of that future—
you know,
developing new nuclear generation,
technologies that had better waste,
management profiles,
that were safer, and all of these other things.
And so that's why I,
wanted to do that in grad school.
So I went and did a research
degree, helping develop the fuel,
cycle for a
reactor that hopefully
will build, someday soon.
See, that's interesting,
because what you're talking about—
you were passionate,
when you were pursuing systems—
you were just,
passionate about
systems Systems engineering,
and we were pursuing nuclear.
It was—
you were just passionate about it.
It
seems like astronaut wasn't, even
on your mind at the time.
Yeah, you know that's a good question.
A lot of my colleagues, wanted to
be astronauts from when,
they were a little kid.
And they definitely were making,
choices to pursue things,
they were passionate about too,
but, always with a mind of keeping those
doors,
open for themselves by studying the right,
things, maybe joining the military.
There's a lot of different,
tracks to get to these seats,
but for me,
I was always looking towards challenging,
myself
as much as I could in each, subsequent
opportunity.
So astronaut wasn't,
really a thing in the back of my mind.
It was something,
I always thought was really cool,
but didn't really picture myself doing.
And so I actually,
didn't become inspired
to apply until,
after I had served on a submarine.
When I left my submarine,
I went back to the Naval Academy to work,
there,
and I got to meet a lot of really,
interesting people,
including a couple of astronauts,
and chatting with them,
talking about the time.
When they were building the space station,
I found really fascinating because it,
reminded me a lot of
the equipment that we, use on submarines.
You're also
trying to keep, people alive in an environment,
where they shouldn't exist.
You know, whether you're hundreds of feet,
below the surface of the ocean, or you know,
hundreds of miles,
above
the surface of the earth,
and so that really inspired me, because I
started thinking of the space,
station as a submarine in space,
and the astronauts who
I talked to really,
encouraged me to keep thinking about that,
and once it
stuck in my mind,
it became something that I could actually,
picture myself doing,
because I felt the role was so so similar.
And so for me,
it was just to always about pursuing,
things I was passionate about,
and that would be challenging because,
if I was doing something I
liked, even if it was hard,
I was going to enjoy it,
and get the most out of it,
and find it the most fulfilling.
So I think, something you see
around our office,
and especially in our classes,
everybody who was
hired was
doing, something that they really loved.
You know that they they,
obviously got their dream,
job by getting
the call to come, and be an astronaut, and they
would never,
trade that for For anything,
but we all in some ways really, miss what we
were doing before,
because we were pursuing things,
we are passionate about,
and so I think that's a common thread,
you see across the astronaut office.
And I think that's right.
Kayla hits upon a point.
I think that's one of the best
pieces of advice we can give folks,
and even especially young folks who may
still be aspiring
to pursue a STEM degree,
etc.,
is pursue something that That
you're
passionate about and that you enjoy.
We receive, thousands of applications
to be an astronaut, right?
And obviously, only a limited number are
chosen,
but it really
resonates when
When folks get,
invited in and get come in to interview,
that they're happy in their jobs and, they've
liked what they've done and right,
they've put their heart and soul into it.
Yeah, that seems to be a
pretty consistent theme, right?
So not
only do they have the qualifications
to become a NASA astronaut,
but they were good and they would be happy
in this
job that they had in
the first place because you're picking the
people that are best in their field,
right?
So, you know,
systems engineering,
nuclear engineering—
you were
one of the best in that field
with
the confined spaces
and living in those areas.
So, yeah, you pull that.
But even if you were still on the submarine,
you would still be happy.
Yeah, absolutely, and I think we get questions
about that a lot.
And people say,
"Should I major in aerospace engineering,
or mechanical engineering?"
And you're like, "Which one do you like?"
A lot of times college students
ask me,
"Should I take Russian?"
I'm like, do you want to learn Russian,
or you know,
they're
just trying to see like,
do I need to be checking these
boxes,
and it's like,
like Anne was saying,
you
do have to choose
certain fields,
but there is a broad,
range of things you can do,
and, you just look at our class as an example.
We have everything from you know,
emergency medicine physicians
to Mars,
geologists to microbiologists that study,
cave slime,
and
a bunch of different military, roles too.
So there's a lot of different, paths
to get to be a you,
know a competitive, applicant for
the astronaut office.
Now, of course,
we're talking about degrees.
I
think we have a really good question, about
just physical fitness from the web,
Jennifer.
Do we have a question about physical fitness?
Yeah, we sure do.
We have one from Twitter from Marie.
Are there particular exercises or fitness
regimes
a person ought to do if they wish to apply
to be an astronaut in the future?
Okay, so I guess just yeah about about fitness.
Kayla, do you have do you have any,
recommendations on just exercises,
or fitness, you
know, it's really interesting.
In our office,
there are people
who are passionate,
about a whole
range of different, fitness approaches.
Whether they like to run,
or do triathlons,
or
participate more in team sports.
A lot of everybody has sort of their own
thing they're passionate about doing and have
fun doing,
and it's important to be fit of course and
healthy because flying in space does a lot
of puts a lot of stress on your body,
but there's no like particular aspect I
think that you have to do.
I think investing in your own fitness,
and health is super important.
But you can do that a lot of different ways.
Okay, yeah.
So it's just once once again,
here's this, it's that same theme—
finding something you're passionate, about—
whether it's cycling,
whether it's swimming,
whether it's weightlifting,
finding that thing,
and just having that be a habit for you,
to maintain that fitness consistently,
throughout your time as an astronaut.
Yeah, and we actually have trainers,
here at NASA who
specialize in advising, us.
Both when we're in space, but also preparing
to go to space,
and then recovering when we get home,
and that's what they encourage.
They say, "What do you like to do?
What are you going to do consistently?"
Because that's, way better
than us prescribing,
you know, a very specific,
regimen
that you're not going to stick to.
Now, obviously, when you are on the space
station,
for example,
there's
only specific equipment,
so you have two options.
But that being said,
they believe that you
can prepare in a lot of different ways.
Okay, so let's,
let's talk about just coming in.
Right, we talked about the application process,
we talked about the minimum applications.
Kayla, let's talk about that first time,
where you got the call that says,
"Hey, we're ready for you to come in."